<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.pointheads.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.pointheads.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-07T23:57:32-06:00</updated><id>https://www.pointheads.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">PointHeads</title><subtitle>The practical guide for the casual rewards traveler. PointHeads provides services allowing credit card users to travel frequently and affordably using points and miles.</subtitle><author><name>PointHeads</name></author><entry><title type="html">Is Hilton’s Price Match Guarantee Worth the Effort?</title><link href="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/hilton_price_match/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Hilton’s Price Match Guarantee Worth the Effort?" /><published>2021-03-07T19:31:40-06:00</published><updated>2021-03-07T19:31:40-06:00</updated><id>https://www.pointheads.com/posts/hilton_price_match</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/hilton_price_match/">&lt;p&gt;At first glance, Hilton’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://hiltonworldwide3.hilton.com/en/price-match-guarantee/overview.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;price match guarantee&lt;/a&gt; looks like it can turn a better deal found on «insert any booking site here» site into an incredible deal booked directly with Hilton.  However, the reason Hilton can offer such generous compensation (an additional 25% off the room rate of the “better deal”) is because they are very hard to find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, claims can be submitted risk-free and are processed quickly. If a decent candidate for a price match arrives in your browser, there is no harm in following these steps to test your luck. For the benefit of PointHeads everywhere, we tested the price match guarantee using a stay at the &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/from_taxes_to_cabo/#bailing-on-hyatt&quot;&gt;Hilton Los Cabos Beach &amp;amp; Golf Resort&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what-makes-a-match&quot;&gt;Understand the Qualifications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Hilton’s “qualified lower price” definition is very strict, often making it hard to directly compare two deals. Choose the deal with the closest match.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#pictures-or-it-didnt-happen&quot;&gt;Prove It&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: In the world of personalized content and limited time offers, a better deal may not be immediately visible to someone else. Capture proof of the better deal as soon as you see it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#decision-time&quot;&gt;Decide When to Submit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Decide whether to submit the claim before or after you book on Hilton. After is more efficient with online claims; before is completely risk-free but requires a phone call.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#state-your-case&quot;&gt;Show the Evidence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The default response seems to be that they can’t find the better deal. Stay calm and show them the proof, highlighting as many matching details as you can.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#marching-on&quot;&gt;Move On&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The final decision will come quickly. If it is in your favor, congratulations on saving an additional 25%! If not, you still have access to a better deal.  Keep your head up and enjoy your trip!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-makes-a-match&quot;&gt;What Makes a Match&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The devil is often in the details, and Hilton’s price match guarantee is no different.  The definition of a lower qualified price excludes an offer with different accommodations or terms.  This allows Hilton to slightly adjust terms (e.g. adjust the cancellation policy) in order to offer discounted rates through other booking services. In the eyes of the price match guarantee, the discounted rate is a completely different type of booking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the criteria for a lower qualified price. The farther you can make it down the list, the more likely you are to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hotel: If it isn’t the same hotel, you have no chance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Dates: Another clear filter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Room Type: Suite vs standard rooms are obvious, but bed types are critical details.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Room View: Language differences like “partial” vs “full” can quickly disqualify.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Number of Guests: Different default values between sites can lead to a frustrating DQ.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Payment Due: Is payment due at the time of booking or not until arrival?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cancellation Policy: How long can you cancel for a refund, and are there any fees?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Included Amenities: Saving the most vague for last. Any difference in the offered amenities (wifi, breakfast, etc.) can disqualify a match.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you get to number of guests and below, it might be very hard to verify a match based on information available in a third party website. It may be even harder to justify a change in price based on any differences in those areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the price match guarantee is not there to justify pricing, only to identify if a better price exists with the exact same terms. And Hilton has the power to interpret whether those terms are the same. &lt;strong&gt;Hilton only allows one claim per reservation, so choose your “better deal” wisely.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_price_match/external_vague.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vague Booking&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Screenshot from payment page on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stayforlong.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.stayforlong.com/&lt;/a&gt;. How would Hilton interpret the vagueness of the payment due date, cancellation fee, and lack of included amenities? For a potential 25% off the already discounted price, it doesn’t hurt to find out if this is your best match.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;pictures-or-it-didnt-happen&quot;&gt;Pictures or it Didn’t Happen&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the internet trending toward personalized and limited-time offers, it is plausible that a deal that shows up immediately for you may not even appear for someone else.  Capture as much evidence as you can about the better deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Screenshot the page showing the most details about the booking. If possible, copy the url of the page that sends you to that offer.  If you can get back to the deal through a url, chances are better that Hilton will be able to find it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_price_match/external_detailed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Detailed Booking&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In our experiment, we used a better offer from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prestigia.com/en/produit.php?idTarget=16979&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Prestigia&lt;/a&gt;. It concretely checked more of the price match qualification boxes than the one from Stay For Long above.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;decision-time&quot;&gt;Decision Time&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With your evidence gathered, it’s time to make an important decision: submit the claim before or after booking on Hilton. While this may seem like a no brainer, there are pros and cons to both. Both cases process quickly. In less than 24 hours you will have a decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Claim before booking: Call 1-800-445-8667 and submit the claim verbally.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pro: This is absolutely risk-free, as you will have a decision before deciding which offer to book.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pro: If the representative has a hard time finding the better offer, you can walk through the steps to find it.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Con: You have to talk to a person, which can be very time consuming as well as uncomfortable/frustrating for some.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Claim after booking: Submit an &lt;a href=&quot;https://hiltonworldwide3.hilton.com/en/price-match-guarantee/claimForm.htm&quot;&gt;online form&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pro: With a confirmation number, the form will pre-fill all fields related to the Hilton offer. You can submit the evidence you collected regarding the additional deal more easily.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Pro: You don’t have to wait idly while Hilton processes the request.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Con: You may be booking a room just to cancel immediately if the decision doesn’t go your way.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Con: Hilton policy is to validate the claim within 24 hours of submission. You may be waiting anxiously for a decision.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the cancellation policies are generous (i.e. ample time to cancel the booking without penalty), the online form is a more efficient method&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  Hilton can do the work on their end without you having to wait on the phone.  With booking and canceling easy to do online, this is probably the preferred approach for many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_price_match/booking_confirmation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hilton Booking&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In our experiment we had plenty of time to cancel, so we booked the room first to have a more hands-off process with the online form.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;state-your-case&quot;&gt;State Your Case&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you found a legitimate contender for the price match guarantee, chances are it isn’t too easy to find.  Hilton will likely come back with a response like the one we received (only 15 minutes after submitting our claim):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Regrettably, I am unable to honor your claim as it did not meet the criteria to qualify for the Hilton Price Match Guarantee.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;In reviewing your claim, I was unable to find a lower rate $1540.78 through the mentioned www.Prestigia.com. Please feel free to share any additional information, including screenshots from the 3rd party website, as a response to this email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where your initial evidence collection pays off.  Send over the supporting information and see how they interpret it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;marching-on&quot;&gt;Marching On&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once Hilton is able to find the better offer, it is out of your hands how they will interpret it.  On the phone they will give you the decision instantly. Online, it may be a bit longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our experiment, we received a decision 13 minutes after sending the requested screenshot. The difference in the cancellation policy was pretty obvious, and that’s the one they picked up on to disqualify the claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thank you for your e-mail and screen shot. The lower rate carries a different much more restricted cancellation policy, while, the booking made by Hilton has a 24 hours before arrival cancel term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very unlikely that Hilton will change their mind once a decision has been made.  Remember, they are only determining whether the offers are the same, not whether one price is justified based on differences compared to the other price&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you get that final decision, go with the best offer (&lt;strong&gt;remember to cancel the booking you don’t want!&lt;/strong&gt;) and focus on enjoying the vacation. Either way, you should have a better deal than initially presented on Hilton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, if you have been following along with our &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/hawaiian_award_trip/#the-ideal-hotel-execution&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;lesson’s learned&lt;/a&gt;, you may also consider whether you could have a better deal paying with points bought during one of Hilton’s frequent “buy one get one” promotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_price_match/hilton_buying_points.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hilton Buy Points&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In our experiment, after the price match was rejected, our best offer with cash was $1,435 from a website we had never heard of before (not to mention the vague details about the booking). The five night stay only required 280,000 points, or $1,400 worth of points strategically purchased during the buy one get one free promotion at the end of the year.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_price_match/hilton_booking_points.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hilton Book Points&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Screenshot of e-mail from Hilton Honor’s verifying the booking with points. Even if paying $1,400 for the full amount of points, this is a clear winning strategy in our experimental situation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Details about the online form submission process (and an example of a rare success story!) can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://frequentmiler.com/hilton-price-match-guarantee-how-i-saved-550-making-2-best-rate-guarantee-claims/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Frequent Miler&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We could argue forever whether 9 extra days to cancel a booking justifies an extra $1,000 in booking fees, but that isn’t the responsibility of the price match guarantee as long as Hilton isn’t offering a booking with the same cancellation policy. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>PointHeads</name></author><summary type="html">At first glance, Hilton’s price match guarantee looks like it can turn a better deal found on «insert any booking site here» site into an incredible deal booked directly with Hilton. However, the reason Hilton can offer such generous compensation (an additional 25% off the room rate of the “better deal”) is because they are very hard to find.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Staying Organized With Credit Card Rewards</title><link href="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/organizing_rewards/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Staying Organized With Credit Card Rewards" /><published>2021-02-28T11:38:40-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-28T11:38:40-06:00</updated><id>https://www.pointheads.com/posts/organizing_rewards</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/organizing_rewards/">&lt;p&gt;As you gain experience traveling on points and miles, you may quickly become overwhelmed with the number of rewards programs and credit cards in your name. Whether you are currently at 1 or 100, there are services dedicated to help you stay organized as you progress from beginner to expert.  The following steps will ensure you have all the information needed to maximize your benefits without overwhelming your brain in the process. &lt;strong&gt;Best of all, the services helping you achieve these steps are free!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/posts/credit_security/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Protect Yourself&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Before anything else, make sure you have &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/credit_security/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;protected yourself and your accounts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#track-your-rewards&quot;&gt;Track Your Rewards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Keep tabs on all your loyalty programs to know how many points you have and how long until they expire.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#monitor-your-credit-cards&quot;&gt;Monitor Your Credit Cards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Maintain a list of your credit cards to remember important dates, high level benefits and when you are eligible for an update.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#purchase-category-reminders&quot;&gt;Purchase Category Reminders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:  Define the best card to use for specific purchases based on the benefits and offers of your various credit cards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#seek-opportunities-to-improve&quot;&gt;Seek Opportunities to Improve&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Check out your transaction history and existing credit card offers for opportunities to better align your credit card benefits with your spending habits and travel goals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;track-your-rewards&quot;&gt;Track Your Rewards&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most critical component of booking award trips is knowing how many points are available and how long you have to use them. As you start traveling, those points quickly get scattered across loyalty programs. For families the effect gets multiplied&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. With each program defining its own expiration policy, keeping track of those points can quickly turn into a full time job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;awardwallet-to-the-rescue&quot;&gt;AwardWallet to the Rescue&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, there are services performing that full time job for you.  Our recommendation is &lt;a href=&quot;https://awardwallet.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;AwardWallet&lt;/a&gt;.  It allows you to group all your reward programs (or at least the 700+ that they support) in one place and update them all with a single click.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AwardWallet’s primary function is to automatically track&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; program numbers, points and expiration dates for every award program you enter.  After updating your accounts, you can see all your travel potential on one page. As a bonus, it can also display your trip information once you book with any of those programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best of all, you never have to worry about those points disappearing out of the blue. AwardWallet will blast you with notifications when expiration dates are approaching, giving you plenty of time to either use the points or find a way to move the date back.
All of this is free, with a fairly &lt;a href=&quot;https://awardwallet.com/en/faqs#21&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cheap option for additional features&lt;/a&gt; for those interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;get-started-with-awardwallet&quot;&gt;Get Started with AwardWallet&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create an account with AwardWallet.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you are interested in a free upgrade to try the Plus features for 6 months: sign up via this &lt;a href=&quot;https://awardwallet.com/?refCode=h4opo8pphi&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;referral link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Send us a message (e-mail, twitter, facebook, your choice) for an upgrade coupon. As of now we only have 10 to provide, but if they run out quickly we may be able to find more.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find all your (and your family’s) reward accounts and enter the information into AwardWallet.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can choose to store your credentials on AwardWallet’s server or keep them locally on your computer, depending on your comfort level (&lt;a href=&quot;https://awardwallet.com/en/faqs#10&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;security info here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set reminders for yourself to periodically log in and tell AwardWallet to update all your accounts with the press of a button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;happy-surprises&quot;&gt;Happy Surprises&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have been traveling for a while, it may be hard to find all the loyalty programs you’ve signed up for over the years. The initial effort to organize them all in one place will be worth it in the long run. You may be amazed at what you find as a starting point from some of those long lost loyalty programs! In our case, we discovered enough Southwest points (accumulated years earlier during the college days) to take us roundtrip to Dallas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;monitor-your-credit-cards&quot;&gt;Monitor Your Credit Cards&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As your credit card portfolio grows to better align with your travel goals and spending habits, it is critical to maintain an accurate history of your credit cards.  Not just to remember important dates like upcoming annual fees or bonus deadlines, but also to know whether you may be eligible for new credit cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;understanding-credit-reports&quot;&gt;Understanding Credit Reports&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;ground truth&lt;/em&gt; for your personal credit card history can be found in your credit report. A side benefit of &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/credit_security/#track-your-credit-score&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;tracking your credit score&lt;/a&gt; is easy access to check and verify your complete list of open and closed accounts, with the officially reported date for each&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  This is the information credit card companies use when determining your eligibility for a new credit card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;travel-freely-has-your-back&quot;&gt;Travel Freely Has Your Back&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To properly manage your credit card portfolio, you need to remember a bit more detail about each card than what appears in your report.  A combination of a spreadsheet (for reminders about details) and calendar (for reminders of important dates) may work for many people. If you are just getting started or just don’t want to spend the time maintaining a spreadsheet and calendar reminders yourself, we recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://travelfreely.net/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Travel Freely&lt;/a&gt; as your card portfolio manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travel Freely maintains a list of all your (and one other person’s) credit cards (including business cards if relevant) and generates a calendar of important dates associated with those credit cards. You only enter the basic information about the cards you have (card name, account holder, date opened) and Travel Freely does the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each card, Travel Freely shows general information about benefits, annual fees and bonus opportunities. It also aggregates this information to highlight upcoming tasks like paying annual fees and meeting bonus deadlines.
Travel Freely also tracks your eligibility for new cards. Its CardGenie tool provides personalized recommendations for new cards, which filters out any ineligible cards based on a bank’s criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;get-started-with-travel-freely&quot;&gt;Get Started with Travel Freely&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simply &lt;a href=&quot;https://my.travelfreely.net/share?ref=12267&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;sign up for Travel Freely&lt;/a&gt; and follow the instructions to initialize your portfolio.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note the link above is a referral link, but simply serves as a tracker for us to gauge interest. There is no compensation for either party by clicking it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Travel Freely is determined to stay free and help everyone maximize their travel potential.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow the step-by-step guide to help you get up and running with a credit card portfolio aligned with your travel goals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;purchase-category-reminders&quot;&gt;Purchase Category Reminders&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you have a couple credit cards, it might be easy to remember which one gives you the most rewards for a given purchase. But as you expand your portfolio to optimize returns based on your spending habits, it might not be so easy to remember the categories that aren’t so frequent. Factor in rotating benefits and/or limited time promotions associated with many credit cards, and trying to keep up can be overwhelming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;maxrewards-knows-best&quot;&gt;MaxRewards Knows Best&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have the time, passion, and energy, you could maintain your own &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.middleagemiles.com/about-middle-age-miles/whats-in-our-wallet-2020-part-3-our-spend-matrix/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;version of a spending matrix&lt;/a&gt;. Otherwise, &lt;a href=&quot;https://maxrewards.co/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MaxRewards&lt;/a&gt; may quickly become your favorite app when shopping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to Travel Freely, MaxRewards monitors your credit card portfolio. While Travel Freely is focused on the higher level aspects of the portfolio, MaxRewards focuses on the day-to-day benefits to help you decide which credit card to use for any given purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MaxRewards is relatively new, and therefore many features are in a beta stage containing the occasional bug.&lt;/strong&gt; But the features and updates are coming fast and furiously, and they are very responsive to any issues if you notify them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;free-plan&quot;&gt;Free Plan&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each credit card, MaxRewards tracks its bonus spending categories (even supporting limited-time bonus categories). It organizes this information by spending category (and even individual business for physical locations) so that you can see the best cards to use before making a purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most personalized experience, you can link MaxRewards directly to your credit card accounts. This allows it to directly parse and update your benefits, rewards and transactions, providing a rewards dashboard similar to how one might use &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/credit_security/#monitor-your-expenses&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mint to monitor general expenses&lt;/a&gt;.  Even if you don’t wish to link to your accounts directly, you can manually customize the benefits associated with each credit card to get basic functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;gold-plan&quot;&gt;Gold Plan&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above is part of MaxReward’s free plan.  If you decide to link your accounts directly, the Gold plan takes this one step further by parsing and automatically enrolling in every personal offer associated with each credit card&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Rather than logging into each account and selecting each card individually, MaxRewards Gold allows you to see and search for them all in one place.  With the Gold plan, the recommended card for a given category/merchant also considers whether you have one of these personal offers available&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to try out the Gold plan, you can refer a friend, and you will both get a month for free. If you don’t want to wait for a friend, you can use this &lt;a href=&quot;https://maxrewards.app.link/kristini9594&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;referral link on your phone to get a free month&lt;/a&gt; right away.  You only need MaxRewards to highlight a couple offers a month that you wouldn’t have otherwise seen, plus or minus the convenience factor, to justify the cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;awardwallet-keeps-you-online&quot;&gt;AwardWallet Keeps you Online&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time of this writing, a limitation of MaxRewards is that recommendations for specific businesses are limited to physical locations. For online shopping, you can utilize AwardWallet’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://awardwallet.com/merchants&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Merchant Category Lookup Tool&lt;/a&gt; to see how each credit card will categorize a purchase before you make it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is part of AwardWallet’s expanding set of Credit Card Optimization Tools.  While most of the tools are limited by which credit card it has access to (only the ones associated with rewards accounts you’ve entered), there can be some interesting information in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://awardwallet.com/transactions/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Transaction Analyzer&lt;/a&gt; as you work on building up your portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;get-started-with-maxrewards&quot;&gt;Get Started with MaxRewards&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download the app and set up your account.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you want to try a free month of Gold you can use this &lt;a href=&quot;https://maxrewards.app.link/kristini9594&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;referral link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add your cards in the top left (at least as of this writing).
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you would like to link your accounts (&lt;a href=&quot;https://maxrewards.co/security&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;security info here&lt;/a&gt;): Via &lt;em&gt;+ Account&lt;/em&gt;, find the banks serving your credit cards and enter your login credentials for each one.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you do not want to link your accounts, or have accounts not yet supported: Add your cards manually via &lt;em&gt;+ Card&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Update point valuations (if you have an idea what you want them to be): Via &lt;em&gt;… More&lt;/em&gt;, press &lt;em&gt;Adjust Point Valuations&lt;/em&gt; and update as needed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At this early stage of the app, it is worth checking the details of each card.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Wallet&lt;/em&gt; view, scroll down to &lt;em&gt;Cards&lt;/em&gt; and view each one individually.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Switch to the &lt;em&gt;Info&lt;/em&gt; view and verify the information, rewards, and benefits.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If anything is misaligned:
        &lt;ol&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Report an issue&lt;/em&gt; at the bottom of the page.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Press the Cogwheel at the top to update/add any Rewards information for your specific card.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Explore all the features the app has to offer and have fun!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;seek-opportunities-to-improve&quot;&gt;Seek Opportunities to Improve&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you become organized and clarify your travel goals, you can start understanding whether your current credit cards are helping you maximize your potential to reach those goals.  There are plenty of blogs writing about the latest best offers for existing and new cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To quickly scan the latest news, we recommend an occasional visit to &lt;a href=&quot;http://pointsbuzz.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PointsBuzz&lt;/a&gt;.  You can browse all the latest news from one page, and focus on anything that might look relevant to your cards and upcoming spending patterns. Occasionally, opportunities will arise for extra rewards on your existing accounts that are difficult to represent in the tools mentioned above. In those cases you can customize your card details on MaxRewards to ensure it is giving you the best recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the time is right to consider a new card (Travel Freely can &lt;a href=&quot;#travel-freely-has-your-back&quot;&gt;help you decide when&lt;/a&gt; that is!), browse through the recommendations on each of your services to get a sense of opportunities for a better card.  Look for cards with sign up bonuses and regular benefits that can help you reach your goals better than your existing cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the services keeping you organized and a bit of occasional browsing, you will be able to optimize your credit card portfolio to help you reach your travel goals in no time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Even children are capable of racking up significant frequent flyer miles depending how often and on what airlines you fly. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;With the exception of a few programs like Delta, United, and Southwest that no longer allow them to retrieve information on your behalf. but even those have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://awardwallet.com/blog/track-united-mileageplus-awardwallet/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;straightforward workaround&lt;/a&gt; if one is willing to share a bit more information. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Be sure to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.annualcreditreport.com/filingADispute.action&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;file a dispute&lt;/a&gt; should you ever find inaccurate information in your report. It could be an error, or it could be an indicator of identify theft! &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;These are the offers that you see when logging in to your credit card account that say something like “get X% back after spending $Y at Z until DD/MM/YYYY” or “receive X bonus points per dollar spent at Z until DD/MM/YYYY”.  You have to enroll in each one individually. If you are like us, you will click on a few until you get bored, then quickly scroll through the rest to see if any catch your eye before calling it a day. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you want a similar experience with personalized offers without linking your accounts, you may want to try out &lt;a href=&quot;https://getcardpointers.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CardPointers&lt;/a&gt;. It doesn’t have a free version and is only available for Apple users, but may be worth a free week trial to see if it fits with your lifestyle. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>PointHeads</name></author><summary type="html">As you gain experience traveling on points and miles, you may quickly become overwhelmed with the number of rewards programs and credit cards in your name. Whether you are currently at 1 or 100, there are services dedicated to help you stay organized as you progress from beginner to expert. The following steps will ensure you have all the information needed to maximize your benefits without overwhelming your brain in the process. Best of all, the services helping you achieve these steps are free!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/organizing_rewards.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/organizing_rewards.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How Paying Taxes With a Credit Card Earned a Trip to Cabo</title><link href="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/from_taxes_to_cabo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Paying Taxes With a Credit Card Earned a Trip to Cabo" /><published>2021-02-20T10:45:20-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-20T10:45:20-06:00</updated><id>https://www.pointheads.com/posts/from_taxes_to_cabo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/from_taxes_to_cabo/">&lt;p&gt;Tax season is not something most people look forward to, especially when one finds out they owe the government even more money.  Last year we found ourselves in this situation. After a few unique events in 2019&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; disrupted our normal tax withholding patterns, we found ourselves staring at a hefty bill from the IRS at the end of the year. While we certainly don’t recommend anyone racking up a large tax bill intentionally, we decided to make the best of the situation and earn a trip to Cabo by paying the taxes with credit cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-payment-strategy&quot;&gt;The Payment Strategy&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Split the taxes owed between business and personal, and earn two sign-up bonuses while paying with a new business and personal credit card, respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-trip-plan&quot;&gt;The Trip Plan&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Fly from Chicago to Cabo San Lucas using miles earned from the United℠ Business Card, and stay at a hotel using points earned from the World of Hyatt Credit Card.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-booking-reality&quot;&gt;The Booking Reality&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;  Due to other trip cancellations, we pivoted and used additional points to reserve our ideal 5 night vacation as far into the future as we could.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-final-grade-b-&quot;&gt;The Final Grade&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;B-&lt;/strong&gt; We managed to book our ideal 4 person, 5 night trip to Cabo with solid reward valuations and $720 in related fees, saving around $1,900 in cash. However, with all the other disruptions we didn’t end up using the points earned from paying taxes. The value of those points is still TBD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-payment-strategy&quot;&gt;The Payment Strategy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our large tax bill made our upcoming expenses higher than normal.  With both of our credit scores looking healthy, enough cash on hand to pay the large bill, and not having applied for a new credit card in a while, we decided this was a good time for each of us to try a new card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a significant amount of that bill due to my wife’s business income, we decided to use a business card to pay for most of the expense.  At the time, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.theexplorercard.com/business-cards&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;United℠ Business Card&lt;/a&gt; was offering an elevated sign up bonus of 100,000 miles after spending $10,000 in 3 months.  This level of spending is normally well beyond the small business’ reach, but these unique circumstances made it realistic.  United has plenty of non-stop flights from Chicago to Cabo. Choosing this card to cover the flight was a quick decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the rest of the expense, we opted for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://world.hyatt.com/content/gp/en/rewards/hyatt-credit-card.html&quot;&gt;World of Hyatt Credit Card&lt;/a&gt;. At the time, it was offering 50,000 points after spending $6,000 in 6 months. The taxes would get us most of the way, and our regular expenses could cover the rest.  We found multiple interesting Hyatt hotels in Cabo with various point ranges from 5,000 to 40,000 points/night. We felt good about using Hyatt points to cover the lodging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we just needed to use those cards to pay the bill. The IRS makes it easy to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irs.gov/payments/pay-your-taxes-by-debit-or-credit-card&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pay with a credit card&lt;/a&gt; for an additional fee. They also make it straightforward to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irs.gov/payments/frequency-limit-table-by-type-of-tax-payment&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;split tax payments between 2 credit cards&lt;/a&gt;. Using the payment to help reach the sign up bonus on our new cards (worth an estimated $1,800 using conservative valuations of 1.2 cents/point) justified paying the additional fee of $270&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-trip-plan&quot;&gt;The Trip Plan&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning from our &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/hawaiian_award_trip/#the-flight-reality&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hawaiian booking failure&lt;/a&gt;, step 1 was to get passports for the kids (perhaps an obvious step for any international travel…).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hanging-with-hyatt&quot;&gt;Hanging with Hyatt&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the hotel, we settled on the all-inclusive &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hyatt.com/en-US/hotel/mexico/hyatt-ziva-los-cabos/sjdif?&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hyatt Ziva Los Cabos&lt;/a&gt; for 20,000 points per night.
We expected to receive 50,000 bonus points and at least 6,000 in rewards from the $6,000 spending.  We had enough Chase points to top up to 60,000 points and book at least a 3 night stay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, the cash price for a 3 night stay was $1,125. This gives a valuation of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1,125 / 60,000 * 100 = 1.875 cents/point&lt;/code&gt;; a great value compared to our conservative estimate of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1.2 cents/point&lt;/code&gt; used to justify paying the taxes with a credit card&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;zooming-with-united&quot;&gt;Zooming with United&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the flight, we expected to book one of United’s non-stop options between Chicago and Cabo San Lucas for 35,000 per person. We expected to receive 100,000 bonus points and at least 10,000 in rewards from the $10,000 spending.  We had enough Chase points (unused from the Hawaiian booking), to cover the additional 30,000 points if needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, the cash price for the 4 of us to fly regular economy roundtrip was $1,990. This gives a valuation of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1,990 / 140,000 * 100 = 1.42 cents/mile&lt;/code&gt;; a solid value compared to our conservative estimate of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1.2 cents/mile&lt;/code&gt; used to justify paying the taxes with a credit card&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-booking-reality&quot;&gt;The Booking Reality&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were approved for both cards, but by the time we received them the world had started shutting down.  The IRS and Chase extended the tax deadline and sign up bonus deadline, respectively, by 3 months.  We were in no rush to part with that much money, so we also waited 3 months before we executed the plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paying the taxes with credit cards and achieving the sign up bonus worked without any issues.
By the time we received the bonus, our &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/hawaiian_award_trip/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hawaii trip&lt;/a&gt; had been completely canceled and refunded, and it was clear that things would not be letting up anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To keep hope alive and give us something to look forward to, we booked a trip to Cabo as far into the future as the systems would allow.
Armed with the convenience of time and additional points from the canceled Hawaii trip, we had the luxury of being very picky while planning.
We wanted a 5 night, not a 3 night, stay. We also wanted a non-stop flight that didn’t require us waking up before the sun.  Thus, our original plan was mostly ripped to shreds in favor of a new one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bailing-on-hyatt&quot;&gt;Bailing on Hyatt&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An influx of Hilton points and better &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/hilton_award_booking/&quot;&gt;understanding how to use the Hilton Points Explorer&lt;/a&gt; led us to the beautiful &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hiltonloscabos.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hilton Los Cabos Beach &amp;amp; Golf Resort&lt;/a&gt;.  In terms of something to look forward to while in isolation, that would definitely get the job done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found a five night stay for 280,000 points (70,000 points/night and 5th night free!). We used the points originally earned for Hawaii to book it without any issues.  The cash price for 5 nights on Hilton’s website is $2,300, giving us an excellent valuation of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$2,300 / 280,000 * 100 = 0.82 cents/point&lt;/code&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After booking we discovered a discounted rate on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prestigia.com/en/produit.php?idTarget=16979&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Prestigia&lt;/a&gt; with the same stay for only $1,550. Using that as the baseline price, the valuation drops to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;0.55 cents/point&lt;/code&gt;.  However, due to our surplus of Hilton points, lack of upcoming travel destinations, and uncertainty whether we would need to cancel, we still favor the points in this scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, this was a great opportunity to try out Hilton’s &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/hilton_price_match/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;price match guarantee&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Spoiler Alert:&lt;/strong&gt; It didn’t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sleeping-in-on-united&quot;&gt;Sleeping in on United&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The non-stop United flights all depart around 9:00am local time.  On the way there, we are happy to wake the kids up and get to the airport before the sun comes up. On the way home, that’s not quite as intriguing. We searched other airlines, but couldn’t find a pair of non-stops that interested us. We decided to split the trip into two one-way flights to get a better departure time on the way home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;departing-on-a-voucher&quot;&gt;Departing on a Voucher&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the flights to Hawaii were canceled, we found ourselves with a United flight credit expiring at the end of the year&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Without knowing whether we would have another opportunity to use it, we decided to book that 9:00am flight to Cabo using the voucher, plus cash for the difference (~$170).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;returning-on-a-bonus&quot;&gt;Returning on a Bonus&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American Airlines offers return flights departing in the afternoon. We like that much better than waking up at 5:00am on our last day of vacation.
Two things make it possible to book an American Airline award flight despite not having enough American Airlines miles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;British Airways is a partner with American Airlines, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://themilesgenie.com/how-to-save-up-to-50-of-your-miles-or-get-2-award-tickets-for-the-price-of-1/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;very friendly award pricing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;British Airways is a transfer partner with Chase Ultimate Rewards, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fool.com/the-ascent/credit-cards/transfer-chase-points-to-british-airways/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;transferring points is simpler than it sounds&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means we can book an American Airlines award flight through British Airways using Chase Ultimate Rewards points. At 11,000 Avios&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; per person, we needed 44,000 Avios for the return flight from Cabo to Chicago.
We originally planned on using ~34,000 Chase points to top up United and Hyatt for the award bookings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As luck would have it, Chase was offering a 30% bonus for transferring points to British Airways. That means for every 1,000 Chase points transferred, we receive 1,300 Avios. With that bonus, we only needed to transfer 34,000 Chase points to receive enough (44,200) Avios to book the flight. Sometimes the numbers just work out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We booked the flight using those 34,000 Chase points (converted to Avios) plus $280 in airport taxes and government fees.  The best cash price we found for the return flight was $900 (including those taxes and fees).  Subtracting our cash costs from that total, we get a solid valuation of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;($900 - $280) / 34,000 * 100 = 1.82 cents/point&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-final-grade-b-&quot;&gt;The Final Grade: B-&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our initial plan was to pay an additional fee on our tax payment to earn the majority of points needed for a 3 night stay in Cabo.  While that plan could have worked, we chose to book a 5 night stay in Cabo without using any of the award points earned from paying taxes.  From that perspective, the value of the points earned specifically from paying taxes on a credit card is still TBD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of booking an award stay in Cabo as something to look forward to while in quarantine, we succeeded. By adapting the original plan, we booked 2 additional nights at a hotel that excites us more than our original choice. We also booked a more desireable flight time for the return trip.  We probably made it more complicated than it needed to be, but with time on our side we were happy to spend more of it to book our ideal vacation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our out of pocket costs totaled &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$720&lt;/code&gt; for the entire trip:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$270&lt;/code&gt; in fees for paying taxes with a credit card.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$0&lt;/code&gt; for the hotel booking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$170&lt;/code&gt; for the departure flight (exceeding the voucher amount).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$280&lt;/code&gt; in fees for the return flight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cash value of our trip was &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$2,620&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1,550&lt;/code&gt; for the cheapest hotel option.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$170&lt;/code&gt; for the departure flight (excluding the voucher gifted by United).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$900&lt;/code&gt; for the cheapest return flight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;34,000&lt;/code&gt; Chase points and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;280,000&lt;/code&gt; Hilton points saved us &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1,900&lt;/code&gt; in cash for our trip.
Our expected value of those points was &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$1,855&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chase: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;34,000 points * 1.75 cents/point / 100 = $595&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hilton: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;280,000 points * 0.45 cents/point / 100 = $1,260&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Confused why we expected such different values from Chase and Hilton? Check out Episode 3 of the PointHeads Podcast to learn about valuations:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://anchor.fm/pointheads/embed/episodes/Episode-3-Evaluating-Reward-Points-and-Credit-Card-Offers-epdcgt&quot; height=&quot;102px&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even factoring in the costs associated with paying taxes, we still exceeded the expected value of our points. This tells us we did a pretty good job in only our second award booking, but there is always room to improve (e.g. increase our expectations)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Related to my decision to change jobs and the sudden acceleration of my wife’s &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/first_business_card/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;basketball training business&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There are also many credit cards available giving at least &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/why_points/#additional-restrictions-on-cash-back-cards&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2% back on every purchase&lt;/a&gt;. Even without a sign up bonus, using one of those cards could make sense depending on the situation. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Rates have since dropped to $700 total for 3 nights (1.17 cents/point), which would no longer be a great use of points. But if we really wanted to get to Cabo while paying minimal cash, it might still be the best option. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Rates have since dropped to $1,700 total (1.21 cents/point), which would be less than the typical United mile valuation between 1.3 and 1.4 cents/point. But the best values of United miles come from flights across an ocean, which is not in our immediate plans.  We could also get 1.25 cents/point by booking directly on the Chase travel portal thanks to the Chase Sapphire Preferred card, but we didn’t have enough Chase points (or a way to earn enough points) at the time. For those reasons, we would probably still be satisfied using miles for the trip. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In line with our expected valuation (0.84 cents/point) had we been able to use them at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.grandwailea.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Grand Wailea in Maui&lt;/a&gt;. And well above most expectations between 0.4 and 0.6 cents/point. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The same flight credit initially used for the &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/hawaiian_award_trip/#fn:2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hawaii trip&lt;/a&gt;. Still a story for another time. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;British Airways calls their miles Avios, because they always have to make simple words sound fancy… &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>PointHeads</name></author><summary type="html">Tax season is not something most people look forward to, especially when one finds out they owe the government even more money. Last year we found ourselves in this situation. After a few unique events in 20191 disrupted our normal tax withholding patterns, we found ourselves staring at a hefty bill from the IRS at the end of the year. While we certainly don’t recommend anyone racking up a large tax bill intentionally, we decided to make the best of the situation and earn a trip to Cabo by paying the taxes with credit cards. Related to my decision to change jobs and the sudden acceleration of my wife’s basketball training business. &amp;#8617;</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/from_taxes_to_cabo.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/from_taxes_to_cabo.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Using LastPass? That’s Great! Using LastPass Families? Think Twice</title><link href="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/lastpass_families/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using LastPass? That’s Great! Using LastPass Families? Think Twice" /><published>2021-02-13T21:22:05-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-13T21:22:05-06:00</updated><id>https://www.pointheads.com/posts/lastpass_families</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/lastpass_families/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor’s Note: This article has been updated in response to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2021/2/16/22285531/lastpass-free-tier-mobile-computer-device-premium-family&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LastPass’ announcement&lt;/a&gt; that they would add more restrictions to the free plan. Since finalizing new ownership last Fall, LastPass has established a pattern of removing features and support for non-enterprise users. We have updated the alternative options to highlight excellent alternatives that are focused on supporting our readers (i.e. Bitwarden for individuals, 1Password for families).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our article about &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/credit_security/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;staying secure with credit card rewards&lt;/a&gt; we originally recommended using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lastpass.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LastPass&lt;/a&gt; to maintain strong and secure passwords.  While LastPass continues to hold a slight edge over the competition for users on the Premium plan, they have secretly been clawing back features that make the Families plan less enticing than advertised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#feature-clawback&quot;&gt;What Changed?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The notable change involves LastPass’ removal of security monitoring from the free plan and all shared folders in the Families plan.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#lastpass-response&quot;&gt;What are they doing about it?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Nothing. Families plan users were not even notified of the change. It appears refunds will be offered upon request for anyone that figures it out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#families-alternatives&quot;&gt;What are my options?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Instead of Families, either use one Premium account for the entire family or seek an alternative password manager.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#lastpass-alternatives&quot;&gt;Is LastPass still the best option?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: For people that can utilize the Premium plan, yes. But LastPass is treading dangerously in the “fool-me-once” waters with their recent business decisions. Viable alternatives are available with 1Password and Bitwarden.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;feature-clawback&quot;&gt;Feature Clawback&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until Fall of 2020, one of LastPass’ most notable features was their “Security Challenge”. Available to all users, this feature monitored all credentials to warn of duplicate, weak, and old passwords. It also had some support warning of any credentials involved in compromised websites&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Fall 2020, Security Challenge was re-branded as “&lt;a href=&quot;https://support.logmeininc.com/lastpass/help/how-is-the-security-dashboard-different-than-what-was-offered-before-through-the-security-challenge-in-lastpass&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Security Dashboard&lt;/a&gt;”. LastPass took that opportunity to remove the feature completely from free accounts.  However, in the transition, they also removed this feature from all shared folders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the main benefit of the LastPass Families plan is to create shared folders for up to 6 family members, this clawback significantly deteriorates the value of that plan.  Now, using the shared folders feature removes the security dashboard feature. You effectively have to choose between the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even worse, there is no indication on the security dashboard (or anywhere else in LastPass documentation) that those shared passwords are being excluded. If even one password is not shared, the dashboard reports results as if everything is monitored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/lastpass_families/dashboard_deceiving_score.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Security Dashboard Deceiving&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Security Dashboard screenshot courtesy of LastPass. When at least one password is not shared, the score is deceiving. “View passwords” will reveal that only the non-shared passwords are included in the score.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only when all passwords are placed in a shared folder does it become obvious that the Security Dashboard is not working as advertised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/lastpass_families/dashboard_no_score.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Security Dashboard Disabled&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Security Dashboard screenshot courtesy of LastPass. Despite storing hundreds of passwords in shared folders, the dashboard does not function.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lastpass-response&quot;&gt;LastPass Response&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LastPass was &lt;a href=&quot;https://community.logmein.com/t5/Support-Discussions/Security-Score-for-Shared-Folders-in-Lastpass-Families/m-p/255236#M24897&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;alerted about this issue&lt;/a&gt; shortly after it emerged in late October 2020.  Based on the responses in that thread, it appears this clawback was a conscious decision made to the detriment of its users&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even worse, at the time of this writing, LastPass continues to promote the Families plan with deception. It fails to mention that shared passwords are not monitored&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;False advertising quoted verbatim from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lastpass.com/family-password-manager&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;their site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Protect your family’s passwords&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;LastPass monitors your family’s email addresses continuously for involvement in data breaches.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Put your mind at ease knowing LastPass is protecting you - even when you aren’t logged in.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Get alerts when your family’s sensitive information is compromised so you can update passwords immediately.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although they seem willing to provide a refund for any Families plan user that requests one due to this issue, they have failed to reach out and notify those users. A majority of users are probably unaware that the plan has changed and is no longer monitoring all passwords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;families-alternatives&quot;&gt;Families Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple options to keep LastPass and the sharing functionality of the Families plan without actually using Families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The simplest method is to consolidate everything into one Premium account. This may be a viable alternative for couples that share a majority of passwords, but larger families may need some organization.  It is doable if you can keep items organized with normal folders.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Place all family members on a free plan, but one (very dedicated) user on the Premium plan.  Premium users can share individual items with multiple people. Those individually-shared items are – at the time of this writing – included in the security dashboard.  This can work if one family member is dedicated enough to manage the items at an individual, instead of folder, level. However, items not shared with the Premium user will not be included in the security monitoring.&lt;/del&gt; This is no longer a viable option due to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2021/2/16/22285531/lastpass-free-tier-mobile-computer-device-premium-family&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;additional restrictions coming to free plans&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these options are not practical, it may be time to look for an alternative to LastPass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lastpass-alternatives&quot;&gt;LastPass Alternatives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two major players in password management are LastPass and &lt;a href=&quot;https://1password.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1Password&lt;/a&gt;. There are many reviews comparing these two in depth, and consensus is that LastPass still holds a slight edge, especially for first time users of password managers. However, with LastPass’ new owners seemingly uninterested in individual users, the battle for top spot will likely be between 1Password and &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitwarden.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bitwarden&lt;/a&gt; sooner rather than later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We encourage everyone interested to look at those comparisons and make an informed decision.  The first page on Google search is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=lastpass+1password+bitwarden&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;filled with worthy reviews&lt;/a&gt;, so we won’t bother regurgitating it here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LastPass Families users are Clark Griswald in Christmas Vacation, putting in a pool with their false sense of security monitoring. LastPass is his boss taking away bonuses without telling anybody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this display of questionable integrity has thrown you off LastPass altogether, the next best option for families is &lt;a href=&quot;https://1password.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1Password&lt;/a&gt;. For a free plan, the up and coming &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitwarden.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bitwarden&lt;/a&gt; is an excellent alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, you can request a refund, avoid using Families, and hope they have a change of heart before straying too far from their mission of keeping families secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nGotsAU1gTk?start=344&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For example, it would warn you if it found an e-mail address associated with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.trendmicro.com/vinfo/us/security/news/cyber-attacks/2012-linkedin-breach-117-million-emails-and-passwords-stolen-not-6-5m&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn’s 2012 security breach&lt;/a&gt;, so you know to change your credentials. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In the suspicious timing category, LastPass parent company LogMeIn, Inc. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globenewswire.com/news-release/2020/08/31/2086214/0/en/Francisco-Partners-and-Evergreen-Coast-Capital-Complete-Acquisition-of-LogMeIn.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;finalized a merger to go private&lt;/a&gt; only a month before these issues started appearing. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To be fair, the technical support team justified that all the features are still present if one were to use the following (completely impractical) solution: Keep a copy of each item from the shared folder in a non-shared folder. The security dashboard feature will work on the non-shared folders, and the family can access the items from the shared folders.  That is, until you forget to keep them in sync. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>PointHeads</name></author><summary type="html">Editor’s Note: This article has been updated in response to LastPass’ announcement that they would add more restrictions to the free plan. Since finalizing new ownership last Fall, LastPass has established a pattern of removing features and support for non-enterprise users. We have updated the alternative options to highlight excellent alternatives that are focused on supporting our readers (i.e. Bitwarden for individuals, 1Password for families).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/lastpass_families.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/lastpass_families.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Hawaiian Award Adventure: Booking Our First Trip With Points and Miles</title><link href="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/hawaiian_award_trip/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Hawaiian Award Adventure: Booking Our First Trip With Points and Miles" /><published>2021-02-06T11:53:15-06:00</published><updated>2021-02-06T11:53:15-06:00</updated><id>https://www.pointheads.com/posts/hawaiian_award_trip</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/hawaiian_award_trip/">&lt;p&gt;Armed with knowledge from blogs and podcasts and tools to keep us organized and &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/credit_security/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;secure&lt;/a&gt;, it was time to venture out and book our first award trip. The destination was obvious: After talking about Hawaii for over a decade, it was time to take action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With excitement levels through the roof, we found our ideal flight and hotel. All we needed to do was earn some points to make our dream vacation become reality. Of course, as first time award bookers, that was easier said than done. Here’s what actually happened, with hopes that you can use our lessons and have much more success with your next award trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#booking-the-hotel&quot;&gt;Booking the Hotel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Grand Wailea in Maui.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-hotel-plan&quot;&gt;What we planned&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: It was go big or go home with two rooms – one booked with a new Hilton credit card, the other booked with a mix of points and cash earned from the first booking.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-hotel-reality&quot;&gt;What actually happened&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Two new Hilton credit cards and a two bedroom suite booked with cash (plus an ocean-view upgrade and 400,000+ new Hilton points for a future vacation).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-ideal-hotel-execution&quot;&gt;What we should have done&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: So many things could have saved us thousands on the booking! The number one lesson – don’t rely on big travel expenses to reach sign up bonuses.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#booking-the-flight&quot;&gt;Booking the Flight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Roundtrip from Chicago to Maui.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-flight-plan&quot;&gt;What we planned&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:  Fly nonstop with award flights via Singapore Airlines – booked with sign up bonuses from two of Chase’s best travel credit cards.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-flight-reality&quot;&gt;What actually happened&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:  A one-way trip booked to Hawaii with cash (with a pit stop in San Francisco), and a one-way United award flight home.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-ideal-flight-execution&quot;&gt;What should have happened&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Add ‘get the children passports’ as a crucial first step for the original plan. Use points on the Chase travel portal even after the other award options ran out.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#the-final-grade-c-&quot;&gt;The Final Grade&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;strong&gt;C-&lt;/strong&gt; It wasn’t perfect execution, but with a partial boost from points and miles at least we had our dream vacation within reach. That is, until we didn’t.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;booking-the-hotel&quot;&gt;Booking the Hotel&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After saving up for a mythical Hawaii trip for over a decade, it was time to splurge. There was only one hotel in our sights: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.grandwailea.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Grand Wailea in Maui&lt;/a&gt;.  With grandparents eager to join the festivities, we needed two rooms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-hotel-plan&quot;&gt;The Hotel Plan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A standard room at the Grand Wailea runs 95,000 points per night.  Hilton members with elite status receive a &lt;a href=&quot;https://millionmilesecrets.com/guides/how-to-get-free-nights-at-hilton/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;5th night free on award bookings&lt;/a&gt;.  For a five night stay, we needed 380,000 points per room.  Starting at 0, that was far too many to realistically book both rooms with points (or so we thought…), but we made a plan to book one of them at least partially with points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://card.americanexpress.com/d/cm/hilton/?&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hilton Honors American Express Surpass® Card&lt;/a&gt; was offering 150,000 bonus points after spending $3,000 in the first three months.  With the Grand Wailea hovering around $800 per night (including taxes and resort fees, which conveniently aren’t shown in the nightly rate), booking one room would easily cover the sign up bonus. With the Surpass’ 12x bonus on Hilton hotels, that booking would generate nearly 50,000 Hilton points and take us more than halfway to booking the hotel with points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apply for the Surpass card.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find five nights when the 95,000 point award was available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Book one room with the Hilton card to accumulate points for the second room.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Book the second room using approximately half points after receiving the bonus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-hotel-reality&quot;&gt;The Hotel Reality&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applying for the Surpass card went as planned, but we struggled to find five consecutive nights with the 95,000 point room (if only we had a &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/hilton_award_booking/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;guide to help us do it efficiently&lt;/a&gt;…).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we struggled to find dates, I suddenly became in the market for a new computer for my consulting business. I signed up for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://creditcard.americanexpress.com/d/hilton-honors-american-express-business-credit-card/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hilton Honors American Express Business Card&lt;/a&gt; and received a 130,000 point sign up bonus for the purchase (yes, I’m &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; kind of nerd with the gaming-style desktop to run the business…). We were now only 70,000 points away from booking the second room entirely with points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the lack of award space availability made us nervous about making two separate bookings.  We also decided that after waiting so long for this Hawaii trip, we needed to stay for at least a full week.  Two bedroom suites for a week were cheaper (and more convenient!) than booking two separate rooms, even after considering the money we could save using partial points. We abandoned the plan and booked a two bedroom suite with our Hilton credit card, directly on the Hilton website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to our Gold status provided by the Hilton credit cards, we were instantly upgraded to an ocean front suite. Booking with the Hilton credit card gave us over 100,000 points in addition to the sign up bonus, leaving us with over 400,000 unused Hilton points ready for a future vacation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-ideal-hotel-execution&quot;&gt;The Ideal Hotel Execution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting from 0 and aiming for a luxury stay in less than six months, we severely limited our options.  With the power of hindsight there were two major ways we could have reached the goal while saving thousands:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buy and Pool Points&lt;/strong&gt;:  While buying points is only a good idea in very specific situations, a closer look shows this vacation was one of them. At the end of 2019 (when we first started planning) Hilton offered a promotion offering a 100% bonus for buying up to 160,000 points&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  That meant two of us could purchase a total of 640,000 points (320,000 per account) for only $3,200.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Using the same Surpass card for both purchases would give us the 150,000 point bonus.  Thanks to Hilton Honor’s generous &lt;a href=&quot;https://awardwallet.com/blog/pool-hilton-honor-points/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;points pooling policy&lt;/a&gt;, that gives us up to 799,000 points to use for the trip, plenty to book both rooms for a 5 night stay. Total cost: $3,200.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hilton Price Match&lt;/strong&gt;: A few days after booking the suite, we learned about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lhrcollection.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Luxury Hotel &amp;amp; Resort Collection&lt;/a&gt; available for many Chase cardholders.  We found the same Grand Wailea suite on the same dates for $2,000 cheaper!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Hilton has a generous (albeit strict) &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/hilton_price_match/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;price match guarantee&lt;/a&gt; that could have potentially saved us $2,500 on the stay had we checked before finalizing the booking directly on Hilton’s website.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;At the time, Hilton had a strict cancellation policy. By the time we discovered the better deal we were unable to modify our existing booking.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big Mistake #1&lt;/strong&gt;: Hindsight also reveals our biggest mistake – using the hotel booking to meet the minimum spend. When the Grand Wailea temporarily closed and sent a full refund, we lost the 100,000 points from the purchase and were no longer above the minimum spend limit for the sign up bonus. This sent us scrambling to ensure we hit the minimum spend for the sign up bonus before the deadline (spoiler alert: we made it work, but it was additional stress that we didn’t need!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big Mistake #2&lt;/strong&gt;: Signing up for the business card offered a significant amount of Hilton points, but not enough to book the room entirely with points. Especially after switching to the suite (where points were in the range of 300,000+ per night), the additional points didn’t add much value to our vacation plan.  We would have been much better off choosing a card with &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/why_points/#prioritizing-happiness-and-spontaneity&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;transferrable points for more flexibility on future vacations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;booking-the-flight&quot;&gt;Booking the Flight&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flight was less of a concern for us. We just wanted to get to Maui from Chicago. Ideally with no stops that could potentially de-rail our vacation. Silly us for thinking a missed connection from a flight delay was the biggest threat to our trip…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-flight-plan&quot;&gt;The Flight Plan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan became clear after reading a guide on &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepointsguy.com/guide/points-and-miles-to-hawaii/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;flying to Hawaii with miles&lt;/a&gt;.  United flew nonstop from Chicago to Maui, and we could book those flights through Singapore Airlines with around 140,000 KrisFlyer Miles. As a Chase transfer partner, we could transfer 140,000 Chase Ultimate Reward points to Singapore KrisFlyer to book the award flight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consensus &lt;a href=&quot;https://creditcards.chase.com/rewards-credit-cards/sapphire/preferred&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;‘best starter card’&lt;/a&gt; for points and miles offered a significant 60,000 Chase Ultimate Rewards® point sign up bonus after spending $4,000 in 3 months to get us started. We had a big expense coming at the time that would get us most of the way there. At the same time, my wife &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/first_business_card/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;decided it was time for her first business card&lt;/a&gt;, whose sign up bonus of 80,000 Chase Ultimate Rewards® points was enough to get us the rest of the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sign up for Chase Sapphire Preferred and hit the minimum spend for 60,000 points.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sign up for Chase Ink Business Preferred and hit the minimum spend for 80,000 points.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After finalizing hotel dates: Find the award flight on United, and call Singapore Airlines to book.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transfer the Chase points to Singapore Airlines to finalize the booking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-flight-reality&quot;&gt;The Flight Reality&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the hotel booking, our flight plan seemed to be going perfectly. Then came time to call Singapore Airlines with the flight information.  On that day we learned you need a passport to book any flight on an international airline. We never considered that our kids would need a passport for a domestic flight, and the plan immediately fell to pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To book the roundtrip award flight on United, we needed an additional 40,000 points. We decided to take the opportunity to extend the vacation, spending a few days with the grandparents in San Francisco.  We found a great deal to get to San Francisco (using an old flight credit&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;). We booked another cash flight from San Francisco to Maui.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used points to get home. We had no trouble transferring from Chase to United to book the nonstop award flight for 90,000 points. And finally we had our first award booking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-ideal-flight-execution&quot;&gt;The Ideal Flight Execution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had we realized the kids needed passports, the original plan would have been fine.  After booking through Singapore Airlines fell off the table, the only improvement we could have made was utilizing the Chase travel portal to book the leg from San Francisco to Maui (assuming we wanted to save the cash, which we did!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sapphire Preferred card provides us with 1.25 cents per point on anything booked on the Chase travel portal.  We had enough points available to book this way had we thought of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-final-grade-c-&quot;&gt;The Final Grade: C-&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While none of it went according to plan, we eventually found a decent use for our points and collected enough in the process to book a future vacation with much less urgency on the earning side.   Most importantly, we got our transportation and shelter booked within budget, and finally had the Hawaii trip within reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a lot of room for improvement on the hotel side. The original plan was constrained based on our desire to use points. In hindsight, the suite was the better option, and we shouldn’t have been so focused on trying to use points for the stay.  We certainly shouldn’t have signed up for the Hilton business credit card without a clear plan to use the sign up bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest lesson was to understand the benefits that came with our cards. Had we explored those benefits (i.e. LHR Collection for hotels, Chase travel portal for flights) before committing to a booking, we could have saved thousands in cash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, Covid blasted the trip to smithereens, and Hawaii remains just out reach. Someday the opportunity will come again. When it does, we’ll be ready to take a mulligan and plan a more efficient award booking process. Until then, we’ll express our feelings through Moana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pnZbiKKydWU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Normally Hilton restricts users to buying 80,000 points per calendar year. But during special promotions like the one mentioned, they occasionally double the limit. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A story for another time: United generously offered me a flight credit earlier that year after Vayama cancelled my itinerary mid-flight before a layover. It left me stranded in Germany while United and its partners scrambled to figure out what happened. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>PointHeads</name></author><summary type="html">Armed with knowledge from blogs and podcasts and tools to keep us organized and secure, it was time to venture out and book our first award trip. The destination was obvious: After talking about Hawaii for over a decade, it was time to take action.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/hawaiian_award_trip.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/hawaiian_award_trip.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Booking Hilton Award Stays Without the Headaches</title><link href="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/hilton_award_booking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Booking Hilton Award Stays Without the Headaches" /><published>2021-01-30T10:30:10-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-30T10:30:10-06:00</updated><id>https://www.pointheads.com/posts/hilton_award_booking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/hilton_award_booking/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor’s Note: The screenshots in this post are modified versions of what you’ll see when you follow the guide on the Hilton website. We are more interested in messing with HTML pages than navigating the gray area between copyright infringement and fair use.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hilton has made significant upgrades to their award booking tools over the last few years, most notably with the introduction of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pointsexplorer.hiltonhonors.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hilton Points Explorer&lt;/a&gt;.
It is easier than ever to find and book a Hilton hotel using points.
However, the Points Explorer is not always the right tool to use.
Here we guide you through the hassle-free way to book a Hilton hotel with points, based on the criteria you have for your upcoming trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#flexible-datesdestination&quot;&gt;Book with Flexible Dates/Destination&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: This is where the Points Explorer shines, but only if you know how to navigate the results.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#strict-dates&quot;&gt;Book a Known Destination with Strict Dates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: This is where the Points Explorer struggles. Using a small twist on the normal booking process is much easier.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#evaluating-the-award-booking&quot;&gt;Evaluating the Award Booking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Hilton’s &lt;em&gt;Points &amp;amp; Money slider&lt;/em&gt; makes it easy to evaluate your award booking once you’ve selected a room.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;flexible-datesdestination&quot;&gt;Flexible Dates/Destination&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Points Explorer is an ideal place to go only under the following conditions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The dates are flexible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You have a rough idea of which hotels/brands you might be interested in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because Points Explorer does not have a “date” filter and forces you to select a hotel using only its name, location and mininum/maximum points per night. If you need to explore some hotels first, it is best to go explore somewhere else and come back with some hotel names and/or brands in mind&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  When you are ready, let Points Explorer find you the best award options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://pointsexplorer.hiltonhonors.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hilton Points Explorer&lt;/a&gt;. Set your points per night limit and click &lt;strong&gt;Search&lt;/strong&gt; (yes, leave the “Where do you want to go” input blank, we’ll update that next!).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_awards/pe_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Example Points Explorer Setting&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;em&gt;In the example, we chose to max out the points.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the new page, you can dynamically change the “Location” input to filter results. Location can be a Hotel Name, Brand, and/or City/State/Country. There is a lot of flexibility here.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Find a hotel that interests you, and take note of the points range. The first (minumum) represents the lowest points per night booked by someone within the last few months. The second (maximum) represents the standard room rate per night from the last few months.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Click on &lt;strong&gt;Check Availability&lt;/strong&gt; to open a new page to book for that hotel.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_awards/pe_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Example Points Explorer Search&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;em&gt;In the example, we chose to search for Waldof Astoria’s in Hawaii&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You will notice that the default dates are set to today, and the points per night may be very different than the ones advertised. This is where date flexibility is important.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;You will also notice that you aren’t signed in! Sign in on the top right to see the points wrapped in a beautiful gift-wrapped box.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_awards/pe_03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book Tonight Before/After Sign In&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;em&gt;Before signing in on the left, after on the right.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On &lt;strong&gt;Edit stay&lt;/strong&gt;, click on one of the dates to open a calendar. Select &lt;strong&gt;Shop by Price&lt;/strong&gt; at the bottom.
 &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_awards/pe_04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Shop by Price&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now you can see the points per night for all dates in a month. Navigate around to find a range of dates with the point values you noted earlier. Use this to define the start and end date for your vacation!
 &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_awards/pe_05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Award Search&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the example, we pretend-like the 5 consecutive nights of 95,000 points starting March 3&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If you don’t like any of the date options, just close the window. The Points Explorer is waiting right where you left it on step 2.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When you find a set of dates you like, click on &lt;strong&gt;1 Night&lt;/strong&gt; at the top of the screen and change it to the desired number of nights. Then click &lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;.
 &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_awards/pe_06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Number of Nights Selection&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the example, we change number of nights to 5.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The calendar will refresh and each date will show the points per night for the number of nights you selected. Select the date to start your vacation. It will send you back to the &lt;strong&gt;Select a Room&lt;/strong&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Verify the dates are correct and a room exists with the points you expect.  Now it’s time to &lt;a href=&quot;#evaluating-the-award-booking&quot;&gt;evaluate and finalize the award booking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_awards/pe_07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Number of Nights Selection&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the example, we verify the terrace view with 2 queen beds is available for 95,000 points per night for the five night stay from March 3 to March 8&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;strict-dates&quot;&gt;Strict Dates&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When travel dates are strict, Points Explorer is more of a distraction than benefit.  In these cases, it is better to use the “Special Rates” feature to find award rates via the normal booking process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Log in to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hilton.com/en/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hilton.com&lt;/a&gt;. Enter the destination and dates of your trip on the main page.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Minor Twist&lt;/strong&gt;: Click on &lt;em&gt;Special Rates&lt;/em&gt; and select &lt;em&gt;Use Points&lt;/em&gt;.  Click &lt;em&gt;Find a Hotel&lt;/em&gt; to see the options.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_awards/nn_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Strict Dates&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the example, we search hotels in Phoenix to thaw out over Spring Break.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The results will appear with the cost listed as points/night.  Find a hotel of interest and select &lt;strong&gt;View Rates&lt;/strong&gt;. Now it’s time to &lt;a href=&quot;#evaluating-the-award-booking&quot;&gt;evaluate and finalize the award booking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;evaluating-the-award-booking&quot;&gt;Evaluating the Award Booking&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you reach the reservation page (&lt;em&gt;Select a Room&lt;/em&gt;) of an award booking you can start evaluating whether this is a good point value for you&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  The page shows the different room types for the selected hotel, each with points per night (e.g. 25,000 points/night) and approximate dollar value (e.g. Rates From $144).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Select the &lt;strong&gt;Book Now&lt;/strong&gt; box (the one with the present) on the room of interest to get to the final pricing information and reach Hilton’s other useful award booking tool: the &lt;em&gt;Points &amp;amp; Money slider&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;strong&gt;Payment and Guest Details&lt;/strong&gt; page, you can use the &lt;em&gt;Points &amp;amp; Money slider&lt;/em&gt; to determine if this booking is a good deal. Slide all the way to the right to see the total number of points for the booking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_awards/ev_points.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;All Points&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;100,000 points for a 5 night stay with 25,000 points/night; the 5th night is free!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now slide all the way to the left to see the total cost in dollars for the booking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_awards/ev_money.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;All Money&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;$815.66 for a 5 night stay at $144/night + tax&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calculate the value of your points: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$815.66 / 100,000 * 100 = 0.82 cents/point&lt;/code&gt;. And the fifth night free makes this a great award booking&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;! Congratulations if you found a similar deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do not have enough points for the full stay, you can always adjust the slider and perform similar calculations to see if it is worth using partial points on the booking. For example, sliding to the middle might give you 50,000 Points + $489.29.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/posts/hilton_awards/ev_mix.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Points and Money&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now subtract that cost from the cost of using no points ($815.66) and divide by the points: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;($815.66 - $489.29) / 50,000 * 100 = 0.65 cents/point&lt;/code&gt;.  Not as great as if you used only points, but still a solid use of points for most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s all it takes. Now you have the power to book a Hilton award stay and evaluate how well you spent your points. Happy planning!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hilton doesn’t have a great service for just exploring. Google is your friend here. To dream big, start with “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=best+hilton+honors+redemptions&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Best Hilton Honors Redemptions&lt;/a&gt;” and see where it takes you. Then come back to book once you have some ideas in mind. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you have any &lt;a href=&quot;https://millionmilesecrets.com/guides/hilton-status/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hilton Elite Status&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, remember the 5th night is always free for Standard Room Rewards! But this discount is not represented in the points per night estimations until you reach the &lt;em&gt;Payment and Guest Details&lt;/em&gt; page of the booking process. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Most evaluations of Hilton points place them between 0.4 and 0.6 cents per point, so receiving 0.82 cents per point would be a great deal for almost everyone. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>PointHeads</name></author><summary type="html">Editor’s Note: The screenshots in this post are modified versions of what you’ll see when you follow the guide on the Hilton website. We are more interested in messing with HTML pages than navigating the gray area between copyright infringement and fair use.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/hilton_award_booking.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/hilton_award_booking.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Staying Secure With Credit Card Rewards</title><link href="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/credit_security/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Staying Secure With Credit Card Rewards" /><published>2021-01-22T19:34:40-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-22T19:34:40-06:00</updated><id>https://www.pointheads.com/posts/credit_security</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/credit_security/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor’s Note: This article has been updated to reflect the recent actions of LastPass. LastPass has established a pattern of removing features and support for non-enterprise users. We have modified our recommendations for help managing passwords accordingly (Bitwarden for individuals, 1Password for families).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you are planning a single vacation or looking to travel the world, reward points can help you get there on a budget. But as you start maximizing your rewards, you will find yourself creating many online accounts and periodically opening a credit card.  While you don’t need to fear security breaches, it is imperative that you know how to protect your accounts, your credit, and your finances from potential issues.  The following steps will reduce your exposure to threats and allow you to react quickly if any of your information is compromised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#strengthen-your-accounts&quot;&gt;Strengthen Your Accounts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: As you manage online accounts, use strong passwords and store them in a secure place (hint: a piece of paper rarely does the job&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#track-your-credit-score&quot;&gt;Monitor Your Credit Score&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Understand the factors that make up your credit score, and use a service to monitor it (hint: never pay to see your credit score).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#freeze-your-credit&quot;&gt;Freeze Your Credit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Restrict access to your credit report to control when new accounts can be opened (hint: it’s easier than it sounds).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#monitor-your-expenses&quot;&gt;Track Your Expenses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Set a budget and track your expenses to reduce the temptation to spend more (hint: credit card companies excel at enticing people to swipe more often).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#learn-more&quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Subscribe to &lt;a href=&quot;https://anchor.fm/pointheads&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;our podcast&lt;/a&gt; to follow along step by step.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;strengthen-your-accounts&quot;&gt;Strengthen Your Accounts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you open accounts for all the reward programs in your life, that go-to password suddenly gets replicated all over the internet. Simple and duplicate passwords make your accounts vulnerable to a potential attack on an unrelated, less-secure website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure you create complex passwords and rotate usernames to keep each account secure and independent from others. When available, use &lt;a href=&quot;https://authy.com/what-is-2fa/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;two-factor authentication&lt;/a&gt; to limit where and how an account can be accessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for help remembering (and even generating) so many unique passwords, we recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitwarden.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bitwarden&lt;/a&gt; for individuals and &lt;a href=&quot;https://1password.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1Password&lt;/a&gt; for families. Password managers are a much more secure alternative to storing them in your browser (seriously, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techrepublic.com/article/why-you-should-never-allow-your-web-browser-to-save-your-passwords/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;never store a password in your browser&lt;/a&gt;). Both of these password managers also have tools to alert you of potentially compromised accounts, so that you can update your credentials quickly&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;track-your-credit-score&quot;&gt;Track Your Credit Score&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you age, your credit score becomes the primary means for other companies to judge you.  With reward points so closely tied to financial accounts, you can protect yourself by keeping an eye on your credit score and understanding how different actions might alter it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the actual computation is proprietary and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdwallet.com/article/finance/new-fico-score-10-t&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;occasionally modified&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.myfico.com/credit-education/whats-in-your-credit-score&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;major factors contributing to your credit score&lt;/a&gt; are fairly consistent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Payment History&lt;/em&gt;: The simplest way to build a good score is to pay your bills each month. This is why “paying off your credit card” is always in the top three on the credit card version of the 10 commandments&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Credit Utilization&lt;/em&gt;: This is the balance on your credit card versus the maximum balance allowed. Paying off your balance in full (and even optimizing when you pay it off) will improve your score every time. Ironically, so does getting approved for a new credit card, assuming your monthly spending stays constant.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Length of Credit History&lt;/em&gt;: This is the age of all the accounts in your report.  Keeping a credit card longer helps your score in this respect. As long as you stay organized and keep the account secure, it is generally a good idea to keep those no annual fee cards open forever to help this part of your score.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Credit Mix&lt;/em&gt;: This one indicates whether you are organized enough to manage different types of debt. It is much less significant than the first three. You can generally ignore its impact, as it doesn’t make sense to take out loans you don’t need just to try to improve this part of your score. Let your lifestyle adjust it organically.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Credit&lt;/em&gt;: Opening new accounts will hurt this part of your score. While it has a minor impact on your overall score, most &lt;a href=&quot;https://upgradedpoints.com/applying-for-credit-cards-bank-rules&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;banks now have specific rules&lt;/a&gt; based on your recent account openings. You must be mindful of how many accounts you have opened to avoid looking desperate for credit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no need to ever pay to see your credit score. If you are looking for free help to monitor your score, alert you of changes and provide tips to keep your score healthy, we recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.creditkarma.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Credit Karma&lt;/a&gt;. By now most banks are also providing some similar free services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;freeze-your-credit&quot;&gt;Freeze Your Credit&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to open a new line of credit, the lender will typically require a full review (i.e. “hard pull”) of your credit report.  To protect yourself from potential identity theft, you can tell the three major credit bureaus not to provide those reports until you authorize it.  This is called a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdwallet.com/article/finance/how-to-freeze-credit&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;credit freeze&lt;/a&gt; and is a mandatory free service provided by each credit bureau&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it does take some extra planning and a bit more time (you must temporarily lift the freeze before anyone can access your full credit report), it is generally recommended to keep a grasp on your accounts while you dive into points and miles.  The process to freeze and unfreeze is straightforward and can be done entirely online.  NerdWallet has an excellent guide for managing each one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdwallet.com/article/finance/transunion-credit-freeze&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TransUnion&lt;/a&gt; gets our award for simplest to freeze and unfreeze.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdwallet.com/article/finance/equifax-credit-freeze&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Equifax&lt;/a&gt; is pretty user-friendly with an online account, but they also make it easiest to accidentally sign up for a service you don’t want&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Make sure you follow the steps carefully and don’t give them your credit card information if you only want to freeze and unfreeze.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdwallet.com/article/finance/experian-credit-freeze&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Experian&lt;/a&gt; is the least user-friendly, especially if you haven’t lived in the same place for more than 2 years.  Follow the guide and you will get through it. For bonus points and future sanity, save your pin number in &lt;a href=&quot;#strengthen-your-accounts&quot;&gt;your preferred secure password manager&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that credit monitoring services like Credit Karma still work while your report is frozen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;monitor-your-expenses&quot;&gt;Monitor Your Expenses&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While earning rewards is great when you use it to fulfill your goals, earning rewards via credit card purchases may pose a significant threat to your finances. Credit card companies excel at enticing people to spend more by offering lucrative earning opportunities.  Before you dive too deep, make sure you set up some checks and balances to keep you from spending beyond your budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Establish a Budget&lt;/strong&gt;:  Whether it’s daily or yearly, total amount or split by categories, find a system that works for you and define some numbers specifying how much you expect to be spending.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set Spending Alerts&lt;/strong&gt;: Every credit card company offers a set of alerts notifying you via email or text about various events. For each card you own, sign in and set up alerts that can help you stay on your budget and alert you if your credit card is being used in unexpected ways. Some of the most useful options are for purchases over an amount, balance exceeding an amount, and irregular uses such as cash advances or foreign transactions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Record your Expenses&lt;/strong&gt;: Whether it’s manual or automated, find a system that works for you to record what you spend.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Review your Expenses&lt;/strong&gt;: Set aside time at regular periods to review your expenses and track against your budget. You can even use a service to send you reports/alerts regarding your overall spending habits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for a service to help budget and track expenses, we recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://mint.intuit.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mint&lt;/a&gt;. With Mint, you can set up alerts to immediately notify you of any irregular spending patterns to make sure your finances are always in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;learn-more&quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want more tips how you can maximize your rewards while staying focused on your goals? Curious to know how reward programs and credit cards became so symbiotic? Check out Episode 2 of the PointHeads Podcast:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://anchor.fm/pointheads/embed/episodes/Episode-2-Earning-Rewards-While-Protecting-Your-Credit-ep39oa&quot; height=&quot;102px&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Just ask the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2021/01/12/technology/bitcoin-passwords-wallets-fortunes.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;would-be BitCoin Millionaires&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For example, did you know about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.trendmicro.com/vinfo/us/security/news/cyber-attacks/2012-linkedin-breach-117-million-emails-and-passwords-stolen-not-6-5m&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn’s security breach in 2012&lt;/a&gt;? With an alert system in place, you would have modified your credentials long before the compromised data went up for sale 4 years later. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Everybody wants to turn responsible credit card use into the 10 commandments. Google &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;credit card 10 commandments&lt;/code&gt; and see how many versions there are! &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A credit freeze is different from a “credit lock”. Credit freezes are mandatory to offer and must be free, while a credit lock is typically a paid service offering some unessential services in addition to the freeze. Make sure you choose the free freeze unless you understand the difference and really want the lock. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I suppose Equifax needs to pay for that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/refunds/equifax-data-breach-settlement&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;security breach settlement&lt;/a&gt; somehow. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>PointHeads</name></author><summary type="html">Editor’s Note: This article has been updated to reflect the recent actions of LastPass. LastPass has established a pattern of removing features and support for non-enterprise users. We have modified our recommendations for help managing passwords accordingly (Bitwarden for individuals, 1Password for families).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/credit_security.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/credit_security.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Choosing and Applying for Our First Business Card</title><link href="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/first_business_card/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choosing and Applying for Our First Business Card" /><published>2021-01-15T20:33:50-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-15T20:33:50-06:00</updated><id>https://www.pointheads.com/posts/first_business_card</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/first_business_card/">&lt;p&gt;It was time to dive into the points and miles world, and we decided to go straight to the deep end.  With my wife Kristin’s growing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.northwestskills.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;basketball training business&lt;/a&gt;, it seemed to be the perfect time to apply for our first ever business credit card.  Having never gone through an application process before, we were loaded with questions and hesitations, but with a bit of planning we were ready to give it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#choosing-the-card&quot;&gt;Choosing the Card&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: With eyes on Hawaii, we identified the Chase Ink Business Preferred® Card as the best fit for Kristin’s business.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#planning-for-the-welcome-offer&quot;&gt;Planning for the Welcome Offer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: To ensure Northwest Skills could meet the hefty $5,000 minimum spend in three months, we needed to clarify exactly what is allowed to be charged on a business card.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#applying-for-credit&quot;&gt;Applying for Credit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Finally confident with the financial aspects, we followed an application guide to see if Chase considered Northwest Skills worthy of credit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#did-it-work&quot;&gt;Did It Work?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Sort of (thanks, Covid).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;choosing-the-card&quot;&gt;Choosing the Card&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We finally took the time to understand the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fundera.com/blog/business-credit-card-requirements&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;benefits of having a business credit card&lt;/a&gt;.
It was just a matter of finding a card that aligned with the business and our travel goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Northwest Skill’s biggest business expense is gym rental space. Beyond that, it is all about transportation costs to games and practices, plus the occasional hotel room/meal for weekend tournaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our travel goal was clear: after waiting for twelve years, it was Hawaii or bust.  The Points Guy provides a &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepointsguy.com/guide/points-and-miles-to-hawaii/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;complete guide&lt;/a&gt; on using travel rewards to get there. We were looking at ~140,000 Singapore KrisFlyer Miles to get our family of four there and back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After considering a few options, the &lt;strong&gt;Chase Ink Business Preferred® Card&lt;/strong&gt; was clearly the best fit. In addition to the 3X points on all Northwest Skill’s gas, tolls, and hotel expenses, Chase (at the time&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) was offering a sign-up bonus of 80,000 reward points for an annual fee of $95.
With the ability to &lt;a href=&quot;https://millionmilesecrets.com/guides/chase-ultimate-rewards-singapore-miles-united-flights/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;transfer Chase points to Singapore&lt;/a&gt;, that bonus alone got us halfway to our travel goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only potential deal-breaker: that generous welcome bonus required $5,000 worth of purchases in 3 months.  That initially seemed like a daunting amount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;planning-for-the-welcome-offer&quot;&gt;Planning for the Welcome Offer&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our biggest (and seemingly only) hurdle was ensuring we could hit the sign up bonus without putting Northwest Skills underwater.  We needed to understand exactly what was allowed to be charged on the business card. From the &lt;a href=&quot;https://applynow.chase.com/FlexAppWeb/pricing.do?card=G5FY&amp;amp;page_type=appterms&quot;&gt;Terms &amp;amp; Conditions&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By becoming a Visa Business Card cardmember, you agree that the card is being used only for business purposes and that the card is being issued to a public or private company including a sole proprietor or employees or contractors of an organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irs.gov/businesses/small-businesses-self-employed/deducting-business-expenses&quot;&gt;IRS’s definition of business expenses&lt;/a&gt;, we brainstormed all the expenses we have that are actually related to Northwest Skills.  In addition to the direct expenses mentioned above, we realized we have a significant number of other expenses that have a business purpose for Northwest Skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Utilities, internet and security due to Northwest Skills’ home office.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Car maintenance, insurance, and registration due to Northwest Skills’ use of our family car.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Laptop and other equipment used partially by Northwest Skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly we had plenty of expenses coming up over the next three months which had a business purpose. The key realization was that while some expenses are only partially deductible during tax season, those expenses are still for business purposes on the business card. We identified enough planned purchases and expenses with a business purpose to cover the minimum spend in time to receive the bonus offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;applying-for-credit&quot;&gt;Applying for Credit&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With confidence that we chose the right card and a plan to maximize the benefits while staying in our budget, it was up to Chase to decide whether Northwest Skills was worthy of credit.  While it seemed like applying for a business loan might be a big deal, we found enough &lt;a href=&quot;https://millionmilesecrets.com/guides/step-by-step-how-to-complete-a-chase-business-card-application/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;guides on other blogs&lt;/a&gt; to realize a credit card application was not the same grueling process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We collected all the required documents, unfroze our credit, and started the application. After double checking all the fields, we clicked &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Submit&lt;/code&gt;. The anticipation built up as we watched the swirling circles, and then came to a halt when the page said &lt;em&gt;the application was not approved&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily the guides prepared us for this moment. Kristin called the reconsideration line (800-453-9719). All they wanted to do was verify the information about the business, and then immediately gave her the good news “congratulations, your application has been approved”.  &lt;strong&gt;The takeaway here is to call the line, even though there was no indication on the application status that they just wanted to verify the information.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;did-it-work&quot;&gt;Did It Work?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We received the Ink Preferred a week after the phone call and started spending based on the plan.
While we did not have to spend anything that wasn’t planned, we did need to adjust some spending to fit within that three month window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three months later we received the welcome bonus.
We were not able to use the points exactly as planned due to reasons that &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/hawaiian_award_trip/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;deserve their own article&lt;/a&gt;, but we were able to book an award trip home from Hawaii with all the Ink points we earned during those three months (plus the $5.60/person security charge).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dollar value of those flights was around $1,400. Thus, for three months we were contributing over 25% of each purchase on the Ink card toward our flight home from Hawaii.
Despite not booking exactly as we initially intended, we still received a significant reward for purchases that we were already going to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Covid arrived before we ever made it to Hawaii. All our points were returned when the flight was canceled, and Hawaii officially became a cursed destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://creditcards.chase.com/a1/InkBusinessPreferred/8tk&quot;&gt;current offer&lt;/a&gt; for 100,000 bonus points after spending $15,000 in 3 months would not have been a good option for Northwest Skills. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>PointHeads</name></author><summary type="html">It was time to dive into the points and miles world, and we decided to go straight to the deep end. With my wife Kristin’s growing basketball training business, it seemed to be the perfect time to apply for our first ever business credit card. Having never gone through an application process before, we were loaded with questions and hesitations, but with a bit of planning we were ready to give it a shot.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/first_business_card.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/first_business_card.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">PointHeads Podcast Pilot</title><link href="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/podcast_s1e1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PointHeads Podcast Pilot" /><published>2021-01-11T21:33:30-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-11T21:33:30-06:00</updated><id>https://www.pointheads.com/posts/podcast_s1e1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/podcast_s1e1/">&lt;p&gt;At PointHeads, our mission is to provide services for credit card users to travel frequently and affordably using rewards earned from everyday spending.
We are pleased to offer the first of those services with The PointHeads Podcast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our pilot episode, we start the process converting Charlie from travel reward beginner to PointHeads expert. We discuss common questions people have when entering the “points and miles” world and the two crucial elements needed to maximize rewards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be sure to subscribe to The PointHeads Podcast on your favorite podcast player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://anchor.fm/pointheads/embed/episodes/Episode-1-Building-the-Foundation-eoocmv&quot; height=&quot;102px&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third party services we discuss in the podcast will help you stay organized and secure as your venture into the points and miles game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://awardwallet.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;AwardWallet&lt;/a&gt;: Keep track of all your reward programs, how many points you have available, and when they will expire.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lastpass.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LastPass&lt;/a&gt;: Securely store and easily access all your credentials (and make your password difficult to hack!).
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Editor’s Note: Due to the recent actions of LastPass, we no longer recommend LastPass for most users. Check out our article about &lt;a href=&quot;/posts/lastpass_families/&quot;&gt;LastPass’ changes for details&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>PointHeads</name></author><summary type="html">At PointHeads, our mission is to provide services for credit card users to travel frequently and affordably using rewards earned from everyday spending. We are pleased to offer the first of those services with The PointHeads Podcast.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/podcast_s1e1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/podcast_s1e1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why We Switched to Points and Miles</title><link href="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/why_points/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why We Switched to Points and Miles" /><published>2021-01-02T21:13:30-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-02T21:13:30-06:00</updated><id>https://www.pointheads.com/posts/why_points</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.pointheads.com/posts/why_points/">&lt;p&gt;For years we were content with paying cash for flights and hotels while enjoying cash back offered by a handful of credit cards.
Last year we decided to focus more on travel cards and maximizing rewards programs.
What prompted us to make the switch?
It was the culmination of many factors that led us to the realization that we could utilize rewards programs to better meet our goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#expensive-family-travel&quot;&gt;Family travel is expensive&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Our travel budget took a major hit once we no longer had lap children.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#additional-restrictions-on-cash-back-cards&quot;&gt;Redeeming cash back is getting harder&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Our credit cards (nearly simultaneously) made it more difficult to redeem cash back via restrictions and higher fees.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#devalued-frequent-flyer-miles&quot;&gt;Being a frequent flyer no longer means free flights&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Despite flying more often for work trips, we were far away from being able to cash in on any of those accumulated miles.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#rewards-programs-and-the-social-security-of-travel&quot;&gt;Rewards programs increase markups&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; The high costs of competitive rewards programs are passed on to customers via (often hidden) markups on everyday prices.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#prioritizing-happiness-and-spontaneity&quot;&gt;Choosing between costs and happiness&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; On multiple occasions we chose to skip big events and alter family vacation plans due to the high costs of travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;expensive-family-travel&quot;&gt;Expensive Family Travel&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once both our kids hit that magical &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepointsguy.com/guide/flying-with-lap-infant/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;age of 2&lt;/a&gt;, our flight costs doubled.
Upon seeing our total vacation expenses at the end of the year, my wife asked “did we even go anywhere?”.
Eight roundtrip flights during peak season to visit relatives pretty much exhausted our vacation budget for the year.
Rewards programs can help us offset those additional costs in a variety of ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;additional-restrictions-on-cash-back-cards&quot;&gt;Additional Restrictions on Cash Back Cards&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cash back credit cards used to earn all of our swipes, with a baseline of 2.5% back thanks to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alliantcreditunion.org/bank/visa-signature-card&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alliant Signature Visa card&lt;/a&gt;.
Then Alliant increased the annual fee to $99 and (following the cash back trend) added a maximum earning per period as well as minimum redemption amount.
Using no annual fee 2% cash back cards (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.citi.com/credit-cards/credit-card-details/citi.action?ID=citi-double-cash-credit-card&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Citi Double Cash&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alliantcreditunion.org/bank/visa-platinum-rewards-card#features&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alliant Visa Platinum Rewards&lt;/a&gt;) as a baseline, we now need to spend nearly $20,000 per year just to break even on the additional 0.5% cash back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other cards added additional restrictions how the cash back could be redeemed (typically only allowing statement credits, with Uber converting to a rewards program allowing only Uber cash redemptions).
Many rewards programs offer more flexibility in terms of redemption options that we could better utilize to meet our goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;devalued-frequent-flyer-miles&quot;&gt;Devalued Frequent Flyer Miles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent a few years traveling across the country (and most recently – until Covid – the pond) a few times per year for work.
While being away from the kiddos due to work was never too enticing, we initially thought a silver lining would be the frequent flyer miles that came with it.
We had dreams of using those miles for fun addon trips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After four years of flying, United thanked me with a ceremonious label of “Premier Silver” status, but we were still far away from having enough miles to bring the family along.
This was a major deviation from my frequent flyer experience in college, when Southwest would just shove free flights in my face for virtually every “Wanna Get Away” fare I booked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned that the increased availability of miles via credit card rewards have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdwallet.com/article/travel/why-points-devaluations-arent-that-big-of-a-deal&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;significantly devalued miles earned from actual flying&lt;/a&gt;.
If we want to properly take advantage of these programs, we need to earn miles in the way that brings the most value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rewards-programs-and-the-social-security-of-travel&quot;&gt;Rewards Programs and the Social Security of Travel&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As rewards programs continue to compete for customers, the cost of maintaining those programs is also rising.
While &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.valuepenguin.com/credit-card-surcharges-convenience-fees&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;explicit surcharges may be illegal and/or frowned upon&lt;/a&gt;, those costs are ultimately passed on to customers via (often indirect) markups on everyday prices as businesses strive to maintain margins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markups are most evident with businesses that offer a separate cash and credit card price for the same items (the only difference being the processing fees), as well as the new Basic Economy fad that has hit the airlines (“basic” meaning you give up your right to a percentage of frequent flyer miles, among other freedoms).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the social security of travel; everyone is paying into the system with every purchase, but only those utilizing rewards programs are benefitting from it.
We decided to take back our portion of those markups by maximizing our rewards from these programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;prioritizing-happiness-and-spontaneity&quot;&gt;Prioritizing Happiness and Spontaneity&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both my wife and I have some of our fondest childhood memories from family vacations, and we hope to provide the same incredible experiences for our own children.
However, with our cash back rewards mostly restricted to statement credits, it is easy for us to lose focus on saving for the greater experiences.
On multiple occasions we chose to skip big events and alter vacation plans due to the high costs of travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We intend to invest in rewards programs (especially those with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/personal-finance/transferable-credit-card-points-best-rewards-to-earn&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;transferrable points&lt;/a&gt;) to help us prioritize family vacations and take advantage of spontaneous events that are otherwise too expensive due to travel costs.
The next time Northwestern makes it to the Rose Bowl, our entire family will be there to see it live.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>PointHeads</name></author><summary type="html">For years we were content with paying cash for flights and hotels while enjoying cash back offered by a handful of credit cards. Last year we decided to focus more on travel cards and maximizing rewards programs. What prompted us to make the switch? It was the culmination of many factors that led us to the realization that we could utilize rewards programs to better meet our goals.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/why_points.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.pointheads.com/assets/images/posts/why_points.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>