<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://pointheads.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://pointheads.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-16T10:55:48-06:00</updated><id>http://pointheads.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">PointHeads</title><subtitle>The practical guide for the casual rewards traveler. PointHeads provides services allowing credit card users to travel frequently and affordably using points and miles.</subtitle><author><name>Isonify, LLC</name></author><entry><title type="html">Choosing and Applying for Our First Business Card</title><link href="http://pointheads.com/posts/first_business_card/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choosing and Applying for Our First Business Card" /><published>2021-01-15T20:33:50-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-15T20:33:50-06:00</updated><id>http://pointheads.com/posts/first_business_card</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://pointheads.com/posts/first_business_card/">&lt;p&gt;It was time to dive into the points and miles world, and we decided to go straight to the deep end.  With my wife Kristin’s growing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.northwestskills.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;basketball training business&lt;/a&gt;, it seemed to be the perfect time to apply for our first ever business credit card.  Having never gone through an application process before, we were loaded with questions and hesitations, but with a bit of planning we were ready to give it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#choosing-the-card&quot;&gt;Choosing the Card&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: With eyes on Hawaii, we identified the Chase Ink Business Preferred® Card as the best fit for Kristin’s business.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#planning-for-the-welcome-offer&quot;&gt;Planning for the Welcome Offer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: To ensure Northwest Skills could meet the hefty $5,000 minimum spend in three months, we needed to clarify exactly what is allowed to be charged on a business card.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#applying-for-credit&quot;&gt;Applying for Credit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Finally confident with the financial aspects, we followed an application guide to see if Chase considered Northwest Skills worthy of credit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#did-it-work&quot;&gt;Did It Work?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: Sort of (thanks, Covid).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;choosing-the-card&quot;&gt;Choosing the Card&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We finally took the time to understand the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fundera.com/blog/business-credit-card-requirements&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;benefits of having a business credit card&lt;/a&gt;.
It was just a matter of finding a card that aligned with the business and our travel goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Northwest Skill’s biggest business expense is gym rental space. Beyond that, it is all about transportation costs to games and practices, plus the occasional hotel room/meal for weekend tournaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our travel goal was clear: after waiting for twelve years, it was Hawaii or bust.  The Points Guy provides a &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepointsguy.com/guide/points-and-miles-to-hawaii/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;complete guide&lt;/a&gt; on using travel rewards to get there. We were looking at ~140,000 Singapore KrisFlyer Miles to get our family of four there and back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After considering a few options, the &lt;strong&gt;Chase Ink Business Preferred® Card&lt;/strong&gt; was clearly the best fit. In addition to the 3X points on all Northwest Skill’s gas, tolls, and hotel expenses, Chase (at the time&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) was offering a sign-up bonus of 80,000 reward points for an annual fee of $95.
With the ability to &lt;a href=&quot;https://millionmilesecrets.com/guides/chase-ultimate-rewards-singapore-miles-united-flights/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;transfer Chase points to Singapore&lt;/a&gt;, that bonus alone got us halfway to our travel goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only potential deal-breaker: that generous welcome bonus required $5,000 worth of purchases in 3 months.  That initially seemed like a daunting amount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;planning-for-the-welcome-offer&quot;&gt;Planning for the Welcome Offer&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our biggest (and seemingly only) hurdle was ensuring we could hit the sign up bonus without putting Northwest Skills underwater.  We needed to understand exactly what was allowed to be charged on the business card. From the &lt;a href=&quot;https://applynow.chase.com/FlexAppWeb/pricing.do?card=G5FY&amp;amp;page_type=appterms&quot;&gt;Terms &amp;amp; Conditions&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By becoming a Visa Business Card cardmember, you agree that the card is being used only for business purposes and that the card is being issued to a public or private company including a sole proprietor or employees or contractors of an organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.irs.gov/businesses/small-businesses-self-employed/deducting-business-expenses&quot;&gt;IRS’s definition of business expenses&lt;/a&gt;, we brainstormed all the expenses we have that are actually related to Northwest Skills.  In addition to the direct expenses mentioned above, we realized we have a significant number of other expenses that have a business purpose for Northwest Skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Utilities, internet and security due to Northwest Skills’ home office.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Car maintenance, insurance, and registration due to Northwest Skills’ use of our family car.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Laptop and other equipment used partially by Northwest Skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly we had plenty of expenses coming up over the next three months which had a business purpose. The key realization was that while some expenses are only partially deductible during tax season, those expenses are not only partially charged on the business card. We identified enough planned purchases and expenses with a business purpose to cover the minimum spend in time to receive the bonus offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;applying-for-credit&quot;&gt;Applying for Credit&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With confidence that we chose the right card and a plan to maximize the benefits while staying in our budget, it was up to Chase to decide whether Northwest Skills was worthy of credit.  While it seemed like applying for a business loan might be a big deal, we found enough &lt;a href=&quot;https://millionmilesecrets.com/guides/step-by-step-how-to-complete-a-chase-business-card-application/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;guides on other blogs&lt;/a&gt; to realize a credit card application was not the same grueling process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We collected all the required documents, unfroze our credit, and started the application. After double checking all the fields, we clicked &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Submit&lt;/code&gt;. The anticipation built up as we watched the swirling circles, and then came to a halt when the page said &lt;em&gt;the application was not approved&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily the guides prepared us for this moment. Kristin called the reconsideration line (800-453-9719). All they wanted to do was verify the information about the business, and then immediately gave her the good news “congratulations, your application has been approved”.  &lt;strong&gt;The takeaway here is to call the line, even though there was no indication on the application status that they just wanted to verify the information.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;did-it-work&quot;&gt;Did It Work?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We received the Ink Preferred a week after the phone call and started spending based on the plan.
While we did not have to spend anything that wasn’t planned, we did need to adjust some spending to fit within that three month window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three months later we received the welcome bonus.
We were not able to use the points exactly as planned due to reasons that deserve their own blog post, but we were able to book an award trip home from Hawaii with all the Ink points we earned during those three months (plus the $5.60/person security charge).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dollar value of those flights was around $1,400. Thus, for three months we were contributing over 25% of each purchase on the Ink card toward our flight home from Hawaii.
Despite not booking exactly as we initially intended, we still received a significant reward for purchases that we were already going to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Covid arrived before we ever made it to Hawaii. All our points were returned when the flight was canceled, and Hawaii officially became a cursed destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://creditcards.chase.com/a1/InkBusinessPreferred/8tk&quot;&gt;current offer&lt;/a&gt; for 100,000 bonus points after spending $15,000 in 3 months would not have been a good option for Northwest Skills. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Isonify, LLC</name></author><summary type="html">With eyes on Hawaii and a desire to separate business expenses from personal expenses, it seemed to be the perfect time to apply for our first ever business card. But are small businesses eligible for lucrative business cards, and is such a small business capable of meeting the large spending requirements to receive the sign up bonus? We dove in to find out.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why We Switched to Points and Miles</title><link href="http://pointheads.com/posts/why_points/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why We Switched to Points and Miles" /><published>2021-01-02T21:13:30-06:00</published><updated>2021-01-02T21:13:30-06:00</updated><id>http://pointheads.com/posts/why_points</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://pointheads.com/posts/why_points/">&lt;p&gt;For years we were content with paying cash for flights and hotels while enjoying cash back offered by a handful of credit cards.
Last year we decided to focus more on travel cards and maximizing rewards programs.
What prompted us to make the switch?
It was the culmination of many factors that led us to the realization that we could utilize rewards programs to better meet our goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#expensive-family-travel&quot;&gt;Family travel is expensive&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Our travel budget took a major hit once we no longer had lap children.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#additional-restrictions-on-cash-back-cards&quot;&gt;Redeeming cash back is getting harder&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Our credit cards (nearly simultaneously) made it more difficult to redeem cash back via restrictions and higher fees.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#devalued-frequent-flyer-miles&quot;&gt;Being a frequent flyer no longer means free flights&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; Despite flying more often for work trips, we were far away from being able to cash in on any of those accumulated miles.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#rewards-programs-and-the-social-security-of-travel&quot;&gt;Rewards programs increase markups&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; The high costs of competitive rewards programs are passed on to customers via (often hidden) markups on everyday prices.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#prioritizing-happiness-and-spontaneity&quot;&gt;Choosing between costs and happiness&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; On multiple occasions we chose to skip big events and alter family vacation plans due to the high costs of travel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;expensive-family-travel&quot;&gt;Expensive Family Travel&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once both our kids hit that magical &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepointsguy.com/guide/flying-with-lap-infant/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;age of 2&lt;/a&gt;, our flight costs doubled.
Upon seeing our total vacation expenses at the end of the year, my wife asked “did we even go anywhere?”.
Eight roundtrip flights during peak season to visit relatives pretty much exhausted our vacation budget for the year.
Rewards programs can help us offset those additional costs in a variety of ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;additional-restrictions-on-cash-back-cards&quot;&gt;Additional Restrictions on Cash Back Cards&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cash back credit cards used to earn all of our swipes, with a baseline of 2.5% back thanks to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alliantcreditunion.org/bank/visa-signature-card&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alliant Signature Visa card&lt;/a&gt;.
Then Alliant increased the annual fee to $99 and (following the cash back trend) added a maximum earning per period as well as minimum redemption amount.
Using no annual fee 2% cash back cards (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.citi.com/credit-cards/credit-card-details/citi.action?ID=citi-double-cash-credit-card&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Citi Double Cash&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alliantcreditunion.org/bank/visa-platinum-rewards-card#features&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alliant Visa Platinum Rewards&lt;/a&gt;) as a baseline, we now need to spend nearly $20,000 per year just to break even on the additional 0.5% cash back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other cards added additional restrictions how the cash back could be redeemed (typically only allowing statement credits, with Uber converting to a rewards program allowing only Uber cash redemptions).
Many rewards programs offer more flexibility in terms of redemption options that we could better utilize to meet our goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;devalued-frequent-flyer-miles&quot;&gt;Devalued Frequent Flyer Miles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent a few years traveling across the country (and most recently – until Covid – the pond) a few times per year for work.
While being away from the kiddos due to work was never too enticing, we initially thought a silver lining would be the frequent flyer miles that came with it.
We had dreams of using those miles for fun addon trips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After four years of flying, United thanked me with a ceremonious label of “Premier Silver” status, but we were still far away from having enough miles to bring the family along.
This was a major deviation from my frequent flyer experience in college, when Southwest would just shove free flights in my face for virtually every “Wanna Get Away” fare I booked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned that the increased availability of miles via credit card rewards have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdwallet.com/article/travel/why-points-devaluations-arent-that-big-of-a-deal&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;significantly devalued miles earned from actual flying&lt;/a&gt;.
If we want to properly take advantage of these programs, we need to earn miles in the way that brings the most value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rewards-programs-and-the-social-security-of-travel&quot;&gt;Rewards Programs and the Social Security of Travel&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As rewards programs continue to compete for customers, the cost of maintaining those programs is also rising.
While &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.valuepenguin.com/credit-card-surcharges-convenience-fees&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;explicit surcharges may be illegal and/or frowned upon&lt;/a&gt;, those costs are ultimately passed on to customers via (often indirect) markups on everyday prices as businesses strive to maintain margins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markups are most evident with businesses that offer a separate cash and credit card price for the same items (the only difference being the processing fees), as well as the new Basic Economy fad that has hit the airlines (“basic” meaning you give up your right to a percentage of frequent flyer miles, among other freedoms).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the social security of travel; everyone is paying into the system with every purchase, but only those utilizing rewards programs are benefitting from it.
We decided to take back our portion of those markups by maximizing our rewards from these programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;prioritizing-happiness-and-spontaneity&quot;&gt;Prioritizing Happiness and Spontaneity&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both my wife and I have some of our fondest childhood memories from family vacations, and we hope to provide the same incredible experiences for our own children.
However, with our cash back rewards mostly restricted to statement credits, it is easy for us to lose focus on saving for the greater experiences.
On multiple occasions we chose to skip big events and alter vacation plans due to the high costs of travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We intend to invest in rewards programs (especially those with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/personal-finance/transferable-credit-card-points-best-rewards-to-earn&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;transferrable points&lt;/a&gt;) to help us prioritize family vacations and take advantage of spontaneous events that are otherwise too expensive due to travel costs.
The next time Northwestern makes it to the Rose Bowl, our entire family will be there to see it live.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Isonify, LLC</name></author><summary type="html">For years we were content with paying cash for flights and hotels while enjoying cash back offered by a handful of credit cards. Last year we decided to focus more on travel cards and maximizing rewards programs. What prompted us to make the switch? It was the culmination of many factors that led us to the realization that we could utilize rewards programs to better meet our goals.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Introducing PointHeads!</title><link href="http://pointheads.com/posts/pilot/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introducing PointHeads!" /><published>2020-12-26T18:19:30-06:00</published><updated>2020-12-26T18:19:30-06:00</updated><id>http://pointheads.com/posts/pilot</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://pointheads.com/posts/pilot/">&lt;p&gt;What a wild year it was. After months of reading blogs, listening to podcasts, building spreadsheets and making plans, we decided to dive into the “points and miles” game and make 2020 the year of memorable vacations.  We followed the &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepointsguy.com/guide/beginners/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;getting started guides&lt;/a&gt;, started &lt;a href=&quot;https://awardwallet.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;tracking&lt;/a&gt; our loyalty rewards programs, strategically &lt;a href=&quot;https://10xtravel.com/best-credit-cards/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;earned credit card bonuses&lt;/a&gt; and even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdwallet.com/article/travel/how-to-earn-and-double-dip-with-online-shopping-portals&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“double dipped”&lt;/a&gt; for bonus points when we remembered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started our points-driven vacation year with a trip to Disney World for our son’s birthday. We followed that with our dream vacation to Hawaii, finally ending a decade-long procrastination.  After soaking up the sun in the Pacific we crossed the Atlantic, converting a wedding in Vienna into a two week trip exploring the Norwegian fjords and Austrian Alps.  We ended the year with a peaceful (and at times a bit wobbly) retreat to the vineyards in Napa Valley.  Thanks to our points providing travel and shelter for cheap, we were able to focus on having a great time during our vacations rather than stressing about staying under budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is how we expected to be looking back at 2020 before Covid came and blew everything up.  In reality, we had to cancel all our planned trips (there’s always next year, Hawaii…). However, even without Covid, we found ourselves struggling to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.travelcodex.com/earn-and-burn-why-hoarding-a-ton-of-airline-miles-is-not-always-a-good-idea/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“burn”&lt;/a&gt; our mountains of points the way we wanted.  While the how-to guides from the experts make it seem so simple, we discovered many nuances and stumbling blocks along the way that may seem obvious to the people who dedicate their lives to this hobby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wild year has led us here, the pilot blog post for PointHeads. PointHeads is dedicated to making points and miles accessible to and advantageous for everyone. Our mission is to provide travel services that allow credit card users to travel frequently and affordably using rewards points earned from everyday spending. We will chronicle our journey from the last year and beyond as we transition from novice to expert – both in the tools we use and lessons we learn – so that you may follow along and take control of your rewards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to PointHeads! We are excited for you to take this journey with us.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Isonify, LLC</name></author><summary type="html">What a wild year it was. After months of reading blogs, listening to podcasts, building spreadsheets and making plans, we decided to dive into the &quot;points and miles&quot; game.</summary></entry></feed>